So here, I want to start with actually the mechanism
that enables neurons to generate electricity.
Because I told you so
there are these electrical signals in neurons.
But what makes it possible?
Why do they generate electrical activity?
So here is a schematic draft or a drawing
of a neuron.
Of course a neuron is not a circle, you saw that it has this structure
but let's look at it as it is, so this blue circle
is supposed to represent the membrane of the neuron
the enclosure of the neuron, there is a membrane,
and there is the outside of the neuron
and the inside of a neuron here
inside of the membrane and the outside of the neuron here
and between the outside of the neuron
and the inside of a neuron
there is this ion concentration.
Okay, so there are three ions, key ions that carry charge
across the membrane of the neuron.
There are the sodium ions, the potassium ions
and the chloride ions, and these three ions
have different concentration
between the outside and the inside of the membrane.
And this different concentration, as you will see soon
can go through, or the ions can flow through
membrane ion channels, which are particular proteins
that might enable when they open these channels
they can enable the flow of ions, let's say
from the outside to the inside or from the inside to the outside
depending on the concentration gradiance across the membrane.
So here are really typical numbers.
So let's look at the sodium ion, you can see that on the outside
it is highly concentrated compared to the inside
so now if I open a channel for the sodium
the direction of flow will be from the outside into the inside.
In the case of potassium
you see it's highly concentrated on the inside
and less concentrated on the outside
so if I open a specific ion channel for potassium
the current flows from inside to outside
and so is the case for chloride
it's highly concentrated in the outside
it's much less concentrated on the inside
and this will enable chloride to flow from the outside to the inside
in case a chloride channel is opened.
So this channel that you see here schematically
is specific, it is embedded in the membrane of a neuron
and when open, this specific ion channel, let's say for chloride
if this channel is open, then chloride will start
to flow from the outside to the inside.
And if it's, let's say, a sodium channel
it will do the same.
If this channel is sodium, specific sodium channel
then the sodium will flow from the outside to the inside
and if it would have been the potassium channel
the current will flow through the channel
from the inside to the outside.
So that's really what causes the membrane of neurons
to be charged, because these ions are charged
and they have a tendency to flow from one direction, from in to out
or from out to in, depending on this gradient
of concentrations and the only question is:
Which ion or which channels will enable which ion to flow?
So if the membrane is completely sealed
completely sealed, no current will flow
and if there are channels open current will start to flow
and when I say current I mean either sodium current
or potassium current, or chloride current.
These are the three currents that enable the neuron
to become an electrical device.
So in order to develop an understanding about
what is really making this gradiance of ions behave like
an electrical device, there is a very well known
Nernst equation here, which really describes
what is the battery,
what is the driving force of these ions as a function
of the concentration difference between the outside of the membrane
particular ion to the inside.
So this is the concentration of the ion, let's say
potassium in the outside, or potassium in the inside
and this, according to the Nernst equation,
this gradiance with some constant here, which you can see
defined in this case here, these numbers, these constants
will give you voltage here.
So this is a battery in units of volts (V) or millivolts (mV)
and the value of thi battery depends from the gradiance from the inside
and the outside of the membrane and on this constance,
which is, by the way this constance
is around 60mV
here.
And Z is the charge of this particular ion.
So okay, now let's look at this Nernst equation
for each ion, so the Nernst equation
described the battery for a particular ion.
Let's look at the battery of the sodium
because the sodium is highly concentrated on the outside
and it's less concentrated on the inside
we'll do this Nernst equation computation, and you will see that
you will get a number of +60mV
this means because sodium tends to flow from outside
to inside, it tends to charge the inside of the neuron
with the positive charge to the level of +60mV inside the cell.
The potassium, and I can see here there is a mistake
if you compare it to the left, so the potassium is actually
less concentrated in the outside
and more concentrated in the inside
it's in Molar (M) here
so there is a tendency, as we saw here in the left
of the potassium to go to flow if possible, if there is a channel open
it will flow from inside to the outside
and this will leave a negative trace inside.
You loose positive charge when the potassium flows
from inside to outside
and this will give you a battery here
of negative charge inside the cell.
So the battery of the potassium is about -72mV inside the cell
compared to the outside.
And here you see the chloride and this is the battery of the chloride.
almost -90mV inside of the neuron.
So these are the three basic ions that generate electrical activity
in neurons and in the case, as it is, with the concentration
using the Nernst equation you can see the battery
for each one separated on their own.
But of course, they are not on their own
because all three of them appear together
in the neuron, inside and outside, as you can see in the left
so we actually have to find a way to describe the combined voltage
or the combined battery of all three together.
So in order to do that, in order to understand how does
one do that, I'm going back to the same descriptions
so there is this schematic neuron, this spherical or circular neuron,
the inside of the neuron here, the outside of the neuron there,
there is this channel or channels that enable sodium, potassium
or chloride to flow from the inside to the outside.
And now, I'll define the voltage across the membrane
as the difference between the voltage outside of the membrane
to the voltage inside of the membrane.
So now, I define V membrane here as the difference between
V in minus V out.
So the difference between the voltage inside the cell
to the voltage outside of the cell.
Okay, and here I want to write down
for the first time in this course, the electrical equivalent circuit
for what I just described until now.
How do I describe a channel electrically?
We saw that a channel is like a conductor:
when open, it can conduct ions through the channels.
So let's call a channel, or let's draw a channel
as a resistor.
So this is now a resistor or a conductance
you know that conductance and resistors are one
over the other.
Let's say, this is the conductance of the sodium channels
which is the total conductance of all the sodium channels
in this piece of membrane, this is the total conductance
of all the sodium channels that will enable, if opened,
for sodium to flow through.
This will be the outside of the cell the outside of the membrane
and here it will be the inside of the membrane.
Here I draw the battery.
This is now the battery.
The Nernst potential for this ion.
We know that it's about something of the order, as we said before
+60mV.
You can see the large part, the longer part of the battery
is directed towards the inside, this means that this battery
is positive inside.
And this is, as I said
the total conductance that will enable sodium currents to flow
from e outside, in this case, to the inside of the cell.
Now, let's look at the potassium.
This is the total conductance of all ion channels
for the potassium and now this will be the potassium battery
or the Nernst potential of the potassium.
This will be the Nernst potential for the potassium.
You can see now that the negative part of the battery
is directed towards
the inside, this is now something like the order of, as we said, 70mV
or something like that
And then there is the third one which is the chloride conductance
G chloride, and there is also
this need to be negative
ok, so the negative side of the chloride is directing inside.
Ok?
And I also want to add something that we did not discuss at all
and this is the membrane capacitance,
because we also know from experiments that
there are these ion channels that enable current to flow
through the membrane, in this direction and so forth
but there is a lot of the membrane that has no channels,
much of the membrane does not allow charges to flow through
and it behaves like a capacitance.
It really accumulates charges, inside versus outside.
So, what I drew now is actually a mode of the membrane.
This is the membrane
this is the outside of the membrane
this is the inside of the membrane
and between the outside and the inside
there is a voltage chain drop there is some voltage
we call it V membrane.
So there is the difference between the outside and the inside
which is a combined weighted sum of this circuit.
So this battery with this conductance contributes something
to this membrane voltage and this conductance and this battery
contribute something and so forth.
And in order to describe the resting potential
which is the basic potential that the neuron sits on
without any particular activity neither synaptic nor spine
now I will have to describe, or actually solve this circuit.
So now I'm going to solve this circuit.
But we made an intellectual jump just now
from a biological description of the membrane
through the Nernst equation, knowing that there are these three
particular ions into a circuit that could be written mathematically
because now this is an electrical circuit and we understand
the mathematics of electrical circuits.
So in principal, I can write the equation that describes
this whole circuit.
Okay, so now that we have this circuit
I would like now to write the equation
and this comes from the Kirchhoff law
and the Kirchhoff law will give me
the description, the mathematical description
of this circuit.
I just want to add one thing:
that in what we call the resting potential
of the neurons, so without any stimulation,
without any excess activity, no synaptic activity
no spiking activity,
the total current
so all the currents going inside and outside
the total current, which is actually
(total membrane current)
which is actually the sodium current
plus potassium current
plus the chloryide current
at steady state, at rest, without any voltage change
this all should be zero.
So based on this equation
I'm now writing the conductance equation
so one thing, we have to remember that if I want to describe a current
over this particular, let's say, sodium path
I am doing the following.
I'm writting now the current
for the sodium current and this is here
so I sodium
is actually G sodium
multiplied by V, which is the voltage drop
across the membrane minus the battery
of this particular ion.
So this is very simple to understand because across this battery
there is membrane voltage, so the difference between
inside and outside, the voltage difference is here
and this voltage difference is multiplied by the conductance
one over the resistance of this particular resistance
for this conductance for this ion
and this will give you the current, the sodium current that flows
across this branch.
This will be true for all the ions
So I could write another equation similar to that
for the potassium and for the chloride
and because I want all the sum of all equations to be zero,
then I get if I just do that, and write I_Na like this
And I_K like this, and so forth
and you sum them up and you equate them to zero
you will get that the resting potential, then the voltage at rest
without any stimulation is equal to G_Na multiplied by E_Na
plus G_K multiplied by E_K, a Nernst potential for the potassium
plus G_Cl multiplied by E_Cl
divided by G_Na plus G_K
plus G_Cl
which is in neurons typically something like -70mV.
So this is very interesting
What I just showed you just using the numbers before that came from
the Nernst equation and using this equation here
to describe current flow of one branch and then over another branch
over the third branch
assuming that these other three current, only the three ions
that determine the voltage across the membrane
I now neglecting completely the capacitance
because there is no voltage change so there is no capacitance current
then I get this equation which is called the conductance equation
which really describes the voltage across the membrane
of a neuron at rest.
The resting potential.
Sometimes it is called E-rest of V-rest.
And I just told you that it is -70mV inside the cell.
this means that at rest, without doing anything
before you get a spike, before you get a synaptic potential
just at rest.
When all of the currents balance each other you get net current
so there is no voltage change, the inside of the cell is about 70mV
more negative compared to the outside of the cell.
So neurons sits because of this gradiance
of concentration of the three ions that I mentioned
all the neurons in the world, sit in a negative potential
inside versus outside, and this is the reference potential
for all the rest of the potentials
for all the rest of the electrical activity
that I will speaking about.
So if I speak about the spike, it will start from -70mV
and then jump to the positive direction.
If I will speak about the synaptic potential
they will start from -70mV, they could be more positive
or more negative, but all relative to -70mV.
So this -70, this
the resting potential is really the baseline, the reference potential
for all other development of other types of signals
the spikes and the synaptic potential.
So this is really the essence of the electrical basis
for neuronal activity.
And maybe I will end by saying the following
this part I will end by saying the following
that the trick of neurons, really the trick of neurons
is to be able to change the conductances very fast
so if I could change the potassium conductance very fast
I will get a more negative potential inside
because of this negativity here.
If I succeed to change the sodium conductance very fast
I will get a more positive voltage inside.
That's the trick of neurons, the fast trick of neurons
to change potentials, both synaptic and spiking
by changing these conductances.
But what makes these conductances change
that's the trick of the membrane of the neurons
which is very unique and this is of course
the next thing to explain to you what is the origin of the capability
of the conductances of the membrane to change
and thus generate new voltages, different voltages
the synaptic potentials and the spiking potentials.
So let me summarize this introductory part
to the electrical activity of neurons
I just said that the membrane ion channels
the membrane ion channels
are the poles are the conductances when open
that enable the flow of currents from the inside to the outside
or from the outside to the inside
across the membrane.
And I told you that the three key ions that play a role
in determining the potential of the membranes
of biological membranes, of neuronal membrane
are the sodium, the potassium, and the chloride.
There are other ions, for example the calcium
but for the resting potential at least
these are the three most important ions.
And what really makes this difference of concentration in ions
enable to generate voltage
is their capability to cross the membrane
and this gradient of voltage skeptured by the Nernst equation
as a battery, so I can speak about the three batteries that determine
the overall voltage at rest and also for other potentials.
We saw the ENA, the battery of the sodium,
the Nernst potential for sodium, the battery for the potassium,
and the battery for the chloride.
And I showed in this conductance equation that overall you have
some kind of a balance between the three batteries and their
corresponding conductances.
So the conductance of the branch that has the conductance
of the sodium and its batery,
the branch that has the potassium conductance and its battery
and the chloride conductance and its battery
the combined equation, which is the conductance equation
determines the end result of the resting potential.
I showed you that the resting potential, the typical neuron is around -70mV
negative inside compared to the outside,
which by the way means that the dominant conductance
at rest is the potassium conductance, and the chloride as well,
but the potassium conductance really determines mostly
the resting potential because it is the potassium conductance
which is associated with
a negative battery of the potassium
it is the one that is the most dominant
meaning that at rest, the sodium is not very conductive
otherwise its battery would influence the resting potential
and it would be more positive,
but because the sodium channels are closed at rest
the battery of the potassium is the dominant battery that
determines the resting potential to a large extent and also
we shall see later, and I just mentioned it at the end
that every electrical activity at least the fast one like the spike
and the synaptic potentials
are the result of the changing of the conductances
these three conductances that I mentioned,
a fast change in the conductance
will change the balance of the batteries or the contribution
of the different batteries.
For example if I enable a change of the sodium conductance
G_Na if it becomes big suddenly, much conductance
many ion channels are open for sodium
then it's battery will become dominant
and the resting potentiel
will move positively,
to something more positive.
And if the potassium channels are very dominant
the value will go more negative than the resting potential
towards minus 80 or 82 or 85 of the potassium battery.
So this is the game of neurons:
in order to generate electrical activity
that will somehow find ways, and we should talk about
the two ways that do it, to generate the spike
or to generate synaptic potentials using conductance change
of these three ions that we spoke about.