So here we come to great explorers, to great investigators
the Hodgkin and Huxley.
So now, I'm going to explain to you, slowly,
the mathematical model of Hodgkin and Huxley,
you see both of them here, that really got there for their
success in understanding the spike
what they used to call the "action potential"
we even use this term today
so for understanding the mathematics of the spike
what is the underlying mechanism first
and how do I describe this mechanism
in order to understand mathematically
mathematically describe the spike.
What Hodgkin and Huxley did, and for that they got a Nobel prize
in 1962, is the following.
First of all they found very, very convenient preparation
the squid that you see in the middle.
This is a very useful preparation because this particular animal
has a very unique axon.
This is now an axon, here is an axon...
here is an axon
of the squid, it's called the squid giant axon
it is giant, it is from here to here, it's a very thick axon,
in our brain, our axon are very thin something of the order of a 1μm
a thousandth of a millimeter, in diameter very thin
but in the squid you have thick big axons
the squid giant axon, that's what it's called.
Giant to the level that it's a half of a millimeter
and this enabled Hodgkin and Huxley actually for the first time
to directly record the electrical activity from the inside
of this axon, because they succeeded to penetrate with a wire
into the axon and really record the electrical activity
or the voltage difference between the inside and the outside
directly in this giant axon of the squid.
As I said, what Hodgkin and Huxley did
they succeeded to take the squid axon here and put
a wire inside an axon here, so this is this wire I spoke about there,
this is an electrode recording the voltage from within
comparing it to the voltage outside.
So they really measured the voltage drop
the voltage difference between the inside and outside.
Before I defined the membrane voltage
as the difference between
the inside and outside across the membrane
I said that at rest the voltage is -70mV
or something like that, inside versus outside.
But what happens in the squid giant axon?
They used a stimulation, they stimulated the axon
because without stimulation it would sit at rest
something like -70mV at rest,
W=without any perturbation, but now they stimulate here
the axon by making the inside more positive
than it was before.
So instead of -70mV, the move the voltage to -50mV
or -40mV, so the injected current inside of the cell.
And here's what they found.
When you do this you depolarize
we call it depolarize, you make the inside more positive
than the rest, so instead of being -70mV
you depolarize the cell to a given level
and suddenly you get this "boom",
this white signal, the spike
it behaves on its own.
We just brought the membrane to this region
to a given threshold, voltage threshold
and suddenly there's a huge phenomenon
something as I mentioned of the order of 100mV
so it's an all-or-none phenomenon.
It happens or does not happen,
and when it happens it has this very prototypical shape.
A 100mV or so in amplitude about 1ms in duration
and then it's gone.
This was the first inter-cellular direct recording by Hodgkin and Huxley
actually in 1939.
They saw the signal.
But of course seeing the signal on its own
does not mean that you understand the origin, the mechanism
the underlying the signal.
And that's where the genius of Hodgkin and Huxley came
because they systematically analyzed in four papers
actually more, but in 1952, there are four papers, A, B, C
and then the D paper, 1952 D, is the theoretical
the mathematical paper explaining the signal in full.
Very beautifully, very compactly, a very beautiful mathematical model
for understanding the spike.
So, first they showed experimentally that this is indeed
and all-or-none, zero and one
phenomenon.
So look, if they stimulated, if they shift the voltage
from -70mV, which is here, by let's say a few millivolts
let's say, to here
they got some voltage response, which decays.
So this is another attempt, sub-threshold, it decays.
But if you reach enough voltage if you depolarize
if you shift the membrane potential
from -70mV enough, something of the order of 20mV
more positive than -70mV, let's say between -70mV
you shift the voltage by injecting the current
into the cell, positive current inside the cell
then you suddenly see this phenomenon rising.
So this is an action potential.
And if you inject it even stronger, inside the cell
you get another action potential.
But all of this action potential have the same shape
and when they appear, they appear in full.
there is no half-action potential, or a third-action potential.
It's an all or none phenomenon.
So it's either sub-threshold, where you don't get a spike
or it's super-threshold, when you get a full spike.
And again, the threshold is more positive than the resting potential.
So the spike starts from -70mV or -50mV
and then it goes 100mV high and then
it disappears after 1ms, 2ms, or 3ms.
So that's the all-or-none property of the spike.
It's a very interesting signal
as I said, it appears in axons and this was very lucky
for Hodgkin and Huxley to have this squid giant axon
where they could record from the inside and from the outside
and can manipulate ion concentrations
which I'll show you in a second
but they could study the spike directly
in this squid's giant axons and amazingly the same mechanism
of spike generation in axon of the squid giant axon
is also true from most of the axons we know today.
So this basic mechanism that Hodgkin and Huxley found
is really universal for axons of many types
including the axons of the different cell types in our brain
that also generate what we call today a sodium spike.
I will tell you in a second why it's a sodium spike.
Okay, so we came to the point where we now want to go into
the Hodgkin and Huxley model.
So before I just show you the description of the spike
how does it look like, it appears, it disappears
it has a threshold, it is an all-or-none phenomenon.
But now how do you measure the underlying membrane mechanism
that enabled the spikes to be generated?
So that's the beautiful trick that Hodgkin and Huxley were using.
They did actually use two tricks, one is called the Voltage clamp
here
and the other one is called the space clamp.
So their idea was to take this wire, a long wire
into the axon and so the axon becomes
iso-potential, because of this wire which is highly conductive
there is no voltage drop between this location
and this location
so the whole elongated axon becomes electrically very compact
because of this axial wire
but also they use a voltage clamp and that's the ingenious trick
that was not actually only devised by them
but also by others, and the idea was to
try to clamp, to determine the voltage between the two
sides of the membrane,
to force the two sides of the membrane
to have a fixed voltage: a voltage clamp.
Why did they want to do it?
Because they want to measure what currents flow through
the membrane when I clamp the membrane to a given voltage
let's say, now I depolarize the membrane by 20mV
from -70mV to -50mV, and fix it like this.
And then measure which are the currents that flow
through the membrane when I depolarize the membrane by 20mV
30mV, 40mV, and so forth.
So I don't allow the spike to occur anymore
because I've fixed via voltage clamp
the membrane voltage between the two sides
of the membrane, I don't allow it to change
and in order to do it, I need to develop a whole
feedback system, so whenever the spike,
wants to start to be initiated, I block it, I do no allow it
because I want to fix the voltage by injecting a negative current
into the membrane to really balance the voltage into my
voltage clamp pre-determined value.
So I control the spike, so to speak
by fixing the voltage between the two sides of the membrane
by injecting negative currents through my feedback system.
And then I can really measure what current I should inject
in order to fix the voltage between the two sides of the membrane
to be fixed.
And that's the voltage clamp idea.
It enables to uncover the ion currents that flow behind
below the spike, so to speak.
So I've explained to you what is the space clamp
and I've explained to you what is the voltage clamp
and I've told you that this electric feedback system
enables to control the voltage very rapidly
so the voltage between the two sides of the membrane will be fixed.
What did they find using this technique?
So here's what they found:
They found that, when you voltage clamp the membrane
above a certain level, so here they started at -60mV
and they jump to 0mV so this is a 60mV depolarization
and using their feedback system record which are the underlying
currents during this voltage step, voltage clamp,
they see something interesting.
There is a very fast early inward current
and a late outward current.
So they fixed the voltage, they don't change it anymore
so it's a fixed voltage clamp
and they measure the current that needs to be injected
in order to keep the voltage clamp fixed
and they see that in the membrane, while doing this voltage clamp
there is first an inward current, and when I say inward I mean
flowing form the outside into the inside of the cell,
later they found out that this is carried by
sodium channels and if you wait enough time
the current, instead of flowing into the membrane
into the cell, it flows outside and this is the outward current
which is carried by potassium channels
or potassium current.
So this was a very interesting finding that during voltage clamp
and later of course I will show that it's also during the spike itself
when you reach the threshold
very early on, after you reach the threshold
there is an opening of sodium ion channels
that are open because you reach a voltage threshold
so these ion channels are voltage dependent ion channels
we'll talk about this in a second
because you reach this voltage threshold
very early on, there is an inward current
of sodium flowing from the outside to the inside, making the inside
even more positive during the spike
and a little bit later on, a few milliseconds later on
you see an outward current, meaning that the potassium channels
are open carrying current from inside to outside.
Ok?
So there are these two separate currents
that underlay voltage change in the giant squid axon.
The early current which starts and then then ends
so it activates and inactivates
it activates and then inactivates
very fast and early, and then later on there is
a current that is activated, the potassium current is activated
and it lasts as long as there is a voltage clamp.
So we call the early current
we know now that the early current is
sodium-transient activated and inactivated
during the voltage clamp, and the later current
that activates later and remains open
remains flowing this potassium current
remains flowing from inside to the outside of the membrane
during the voltage clamp.
So these are the two basic currents that Hodgkin and Huxley found
that underlie the generation of the spike
in the membrane of the squid giant axon.
What did they do next?
Next they did voltage clamp to different levels.
Here is an example of voltage clamps to different levels.
So from -60 to -40 from -60 to -20, and so forth
so they clamped the membrane to different levels
and they measured these two currents that I've mentioned before.
The early sodium current
now reversed just for the purpose of showing it
but it should have been inward, it should've been in this direction
in this direction
so this is the early inward current that is carried by sodium
and this is the late current, the potassium current
that is late relative to the early one, during voltage clamp.
So this is what Hodgkin and Huxley did
they tried to decipher, to analyze separately
mathematically how to describe the early current
and how to describe the late current
the potassium current mathematically.
Because they had all these measurements
they could fit mathematical equations
for each one of these currents.
The important thing to know here, and you already can see it here
is that the currents themselves, both potassium and sodium
are both voltage dependent, because you can see
if I change the voltage
I get different currents, but it's also time dependent
as we said before.
The first one is this sodium, and it's very important
that the first early current in voltage clamp is the sodium current
going inward, and this also changes in time as you get more
depolarization.
So it's for small depolarization, you get a slower inward current
of sodium
for a larger depolarization, you'll get a faster sodium current
and also a bigger sodium current.
So these are currents that are both voltage and time dependent.
So in principle, I should be able and that's what Hodgkin and Huxley
tried to do.
To describe the conductance of, let's say, the potassium
as a function of time and of membrane voltage.
Similar to the sodium channels.
So this is the sodium conductance but this conductance depends
both on time and on voltage.
So I should tell you now, without going into the details
that we know today that in the axons there are these marvelous, unique
absolutely unique ion channels that carry potassium and sodium
as we discussed before, but in this case
these ion channels that are in the axons
are sensitive to voltage
They are voltage dependent.
So what makes these channels open and close
is voltage.
They are sensitive to voltage.
These are voltage dependent ion channels.
That's why I wrote that the conductance here
of the sodium is voltage dependent.
It also takes time for this conductance to open
so it's also time dependent.
So these are very unique channels
they are mostly embedded in the membrane of the axon
so the axon is absolutely decorated very densely
with voltage dependance ion channels
both for potassium and sodium
and these channels are the channels
that enable the generation of the spike
as I will show you in a second.
So, let's continue with the Hodgkin and Huxley discovery.
So first of all, Hodgkin and Huxley
drew this circuit.
Here's the Hodgkin and Huxley
circuit of the squid giant axon membrane
and as you can see here, there are these
sodium channels that are voltage and time dependent,
there are potassium conductances that are voltage and time dependent,
and there is this thing that we call Leak conductance
which is the conductance that is not voltage dependent
these are what we sometimes call "the passive conductance"
these are all other ion channels, sodium, potassium, and chloride
that do not depend on voltage.
So these are the two channels, the potassium and the sodium
that are voltage dependent that
underlie the generation of the spike.
And here you see the membrane capacitance
which are, as I said, all the other things
that are not channels, which can accumulate ions
inside and outside of the membrane.
By the way, in this case they drew the case upside down
so this is the inside, so this is the negative part
of the neuron and this is the outside
which they connected to ground.
And this is the total of the Hodgkin and Huxley
equation here, so the current that flows
through the membrane
through this piece of model membrane here
is a sum of the capacitative current
so we didn't go into it, but the capacitative current
is always the capacitant C multiplied by derivative with time
dV/dt of the voltage across the membrane
so this is the voltage across the membrane V
as we discussed before.
So this is a voltage equation here
and it's actually currents, so the total membrane current here
is the sum of the capacitance current
the capacitance plus the sodium current I_Na
you already saw equation, but in this case
you have this sodium conductance which is voltage and time dependent.
It's an excitable channel, it's a voltage dependent channel
similarly to the potassium current
and also the leak one, but here it's a mistake, you see
the leak voltage is independent, so this is I_Leak.
So this is the total current that flows through the membrane
during the spike.
The question is, can we use the clamp
and the measurements they did of the dependence
of membrane currents on voltage, to now describe
the generation of the spike, because remember
the spike itself is a voltage change
it's not a voltage clamp, because it changes
from time to time, changes, changes, and then goes down
but for each voltage, we know from the voltage clamp
what are the supposingly currents
both potassium and sodium, they go through the membrane
in this voltage, and then in this voltage
so the voltage clam was a tool to study the dependence
of this current on voltage and then use it
to try to mathematically describe the transient behavior of the spike
using what we learned from the voltage clamp.
Of course, as they succeeded, otherwise they wouldn't get
the Nobel prize, because they did a wonderful work in transforming
from what they learned form the voltage clamp
into describing the spike.
So here it is.
This is one example of a voltage clamp experiment
and a mathematical attempt to capture the current that
they measure, so the continuous line here
this line
is the theoretical line and these dots
are the experimental dots measured by Hodgkin and Huxley
for this particular step
and then they used this equation
to try to describe, in this case
the conductance of the potassium.
So this is the conductance of the potassium.
They say that they can fit very well this particular
experimental result by describing
the conductance, so this is again
a function of T and V
yes
by maximal conductance, so this is a total
conductance of potassium in a piece of membrane
if everything would've openned, you would get this
total conductance of the potassium
multiplied by some parameter which they call "n"
the activation variable.
And this "n" is a parameter. that in some sense
it tells you which proportions, what is the proportion
of the ions available, potassium ions available
in the membrane that are open.
So "n" goes from 0 to 1.
So if it's zero there is no conductance
for potassium, everything is closed
and it's one, it's the maximal
all the channels are open.
So that's how Hodgkin and Huxley thought
about the potassium channels, and they realized that this "n"
this "n" parameter
as I said, it also depends on voltage
and on time.
So this probability, or this parameter
between zero and one, that can be thought of as
probability,
this probability to be open, the channel probability to be open
depends on voltage, so the more voltage
depolarization you have
the more probability that the channel will be open,
but it will also take some time for this channel to open
and this time dependence is also voltage dependence.
Ok, so that's the channel.
Here is the complete equation of Hodgkin and Huxley
you just saw this one.
And now they describe this parameter "n" here
by two extra additional parameters
αn and βn
these are the rate constances by which the channel opens
or closes.
So this is the closed state of the channel
and this is the rate by which the closed state of the channel
tends to open,
and βn is the rate by which the open state of the channel
tends to close.
So that's how they describe this activation function "n"
for the potassium to depend on these rate functions
of the channel, like a chemical reaction
either to go towards the closed state of the channel
or to go towards the open state of the channel
and this is the description of this channel
and beta and alpha are both voltage dependent.
So this is voltage dependent, and this is voltage independent
and eventually "n", of course, is both time and voltage dependent.
So that's the Hodgkin and Huxley equation for the potassium channel.
It has a conductance, the conductance depends
on this activation variable "n", and this activation variable n""
depends on the activation rate of making the closed channel open
Alpha "n", and the activation rate, activation function
in units of 1 over time, of making the open channel close.
And as I said, the α and the β
are both only voltage dependent.
"n" is both time and voltage dependent.
And now they try to fit this whole equation,
this hole experimental behavior, so this is the continuous line here
they are trying to do a good mathematical approximation
and they found these two equations both for α
as a function of V, and for β as a function of V.
These two particular equation without getting into the details
of why they choose this particularity equation
they had the intuition of how this equation should look like
and they fit the numbers here and here, and so on
and they get a wonderful fit as you see here
between the experimental results and the theoretical curve.
So this is sketchuring... these equations
now capture the behavior of the potassium current
or the potassium conductance.
They did the same thing for the sodium
the sodium is more complicated, here is a voltage clamp experiment
so they clamp it to this voltage, and to a bigger voltage
and to a larger voltage, and so forth
and they got this set of curves and now they are trying to
do the exact same procedure, like they do for the potassium
separately for sodium.
This is more complicated, because as discussed before
the sodium first activates and then inactivates
The sodium first activates and then, although you continue
to hold the voltage clamp, it goes down.
So there are two stages, separate stages
to the sodium channel.
It activates during the polarization but at the same time
it also starts to inactivate.
So that's what makes the equation more difficult.
So there is this "m" variable, which behaves like the "n" variable
but the activation of the sodium channels
and this "h" variable is for the inactivation
of the sodium channels, but in principal
they are absolutely same equations
with alpha "m" and beta "m", and alpha "h" and beta "h"
very similar, each one has it's own
prototypical equation for the description
and here they are for the α "m" and for the β "m"
so this is the activation of the sodium channel.
and this is for the inactivation .
So again this is an attempt by Hodgkin and Huxley
to fit these continuous lines here
continuous line here
are the fit to the experimental dots using these equations.
Ok, so they use the voltage clamp in order to get these equations
and now they are trying to simulate mathematically
all three equations, actually more than three equations
because you have for alpha and beta, and so forth
the set of equations together in order to try to see whether they
can replicate mathematically, capture the full action potential.
And here is the result.
This is now the circuit that I mentioned before
of all the channels involved.
These are actually the four basic Hodgkin and Huxley equations
this is the current equation depending on the capacitance current
the sodium current, the potassium current and the Leak current,
and these are three more equations for the activation of the "m"
of the sodium activation, the activation of the potassium "n"
and the inactivation of the sodium "h".
So these are the four basic Hodgkin and Huxley equations
and now you know we also have
equations for the alphas and the betas
for each one of them separately
using all of these four equations
plus the equations for alpha and beta
in a rather old primitive computer, compared to what we have today,
they succeeded to get the full action potential.
Here's the first time you see a simulated
action potential.
So this is the voltage, the solution for this equation
that I showed you before
is the solution for the voltage.
So here is the voltage solved by the Hodgkin and Huxley equation
and you see that the voltage behaves very similarly
to an action potential.
It grows and then it goes down
even bellow the resting potential, and then it terminates.
But of course they could also see the underlying mechanism
because they had a model, for example
you can see that the conductance of the sodium
is the early conductance is the one that initiates
the action potential.
Why?
Because very early on when the action potential starts growing
if you depolarize the membrane enough
this depolarization very early on opens sodium channels
sodium starts flowing into the cell
and then charges the inside of the cell with
positive charge, so the inside of the cell becomes more positive
and then more sodium channels are open
more sodium channels are now carrying sodium charge
into the cell
and the cell becomes more and more positive inside
and this is the blowing of the spike.
But later on, the potassium channels start to open and
potassium channels are later, but they start to open
this now means that the potassium escapes from inside to the outside
due to this gradience potassium leaves the inside of the cell
the potassium ion channels, and this makes the inside
more negative, more negative meaning that you end the action potential
and here even more negative because here there is a lot of
conductance for potassium here and the sodium almost ended
so now the potassium carries membrane potential bellow rest
towards the Nernst battery of the potassium
and then potassium closes a little bit slowly
and then ends the complete phenomenon.
So you'll now realize that the action potential
which actually looks very similar to the biological action potential
by Hodgkin and Huxley equations, is a really good description
of the biological phenomenon that we call spike
or action potential.
So, let me summarize this part.
So as I sad, the Hodgkin and Huxley
is really a marvelous success
of taking biological measurements,
many years of biological measurements
of what ions are involved involved
changing the concentration in sodium and potassium,
but eventually coming to an equation,
a set of four equations,
with some extra equation to describe the rate constance, Alpha and Beta,
and then you get a wonderful description
of this phenomenon that is called the spike.
We know that the spike is carried by two ions,
two main ions potassium and sodium
and that's the main thing
depend on voltage, so these two ions, the capability of two ions
to flow through the membrane, depends on particular channels
in the membrane.
Hodgkin and Huxley used to call them gates
these are gates that are opening and closing the membrane
and these gates are themselves voltage dependent.
So you have a phenomenon that is a voltage phenomenon
the spike, but the voltage of the spike itself
open the channels, first early channels
the sodium channels, which make the spike itself
grow because the spike in the beginning
insert more and more sodium channels into the axon
and more and more of these sodium channels
make the inside more and more positive
until it blows regeneratively, we call it
but then later on the potassium comes in
and the voltage opens the potassium channels
in the membrane.
These potassium channels enable potassium to flow
from the inside to the outside, leaving negative traces inside
and these negative traces inside make
the spike go off,
shut off, turn off.
So this interplay between the fast inward
inactivating  sodium, and the late outward
activated potassium is really the underlying mechanism
of this fantastic phenomenon, the spike.
So the capability of spike to occur in the axon
critically and totally depend on the existence of
specific ion channels in the axons
that are themselves sensitive to voltage.
They are voltage dependent, or what we call "excitable channels"
and this excitability of the channels
enables the spikes to regenerate itself
and blow itself up and then close itself due to the potassium.
So that's what I wanted to say about
the Hodgkin and Huxley equations.
Now, of course, we have fast computers which I hope you will use
your own computer can simulate the Hodgkin and Huxley equation
very fast, Hodgkin and Huxley worked very hard to solve
the equation numerically, but they eventually succeeded
and they got something very nice comparable to what they measured
experimentally.
Before ending this part, I want to say two things.
First of all, as I said
when solving the four equations Hodgkin and Huxley succeeded
to replicate the experimental spike
but not only replicate, and that's a very important
point that I want to make here about a good model.
A good model is not only a replica, of what you already put inside.
A good model, which is very useful for biologists, for example
is a model that gives prediction.
And one of the main predictions of Hodgkin and Huxley is that
after the spike, following the spike
there is a period where you cannot get a second spike.
It's called a refractory period.
This was not a part of the initial model but it was explained
by the Hodgkin and Huxley model, so it's a prediction
by a Hodgkin and Huxley model, we know experimentally
that when you stimulate the axon and very early on
you stimulate again another axon, it won't generate a second spike.
So there is a period, whereby we cannot get a second spike.
It's a very important period, the refractory period
because it sets the frequency of spikes
that the axon can generate.
One spike, and then stop, no spike,
no matter what you do
and then a second spike.
It's called the refractory period, let's say every 10ms
you can get a spike, this means
hundred spikes per second, hundred hertz.
So the Hodgkin and Huxley model prejudiced and explained
the phenomenon of the refractory period.
In the same 1952-D paper also predicted the velocity of
the spike, which is not a part of this local model.
The velocity of the spike depends on the length of the axon
the width of the axon
they predicted the velocity of the spike
in the squid giant axon, in their mathematical equation
and it was really, indeed
the same velocity measured experimentally.
So this is a very powerful model because it doesn't only replicate
the experimental result, but it explained other results
that were not part of the original model.
And finally, I want to say something very important
which I already highlighted or mentioned before
is that the Hodgkin and Huxley model is a universal model
in the sense that, no matter what cell you take
let's say, now I take for you this cell, which is
a pyramidal cell reconstructed from the cortex, actually
human cell, human pyramidal cell, you saw before, and this is the axon
of this human pyramidal cell, or this is a piece of an axon
And you can see that, if you measure
in this particular cell
if you measure in this particular cell
the spiking activity, you get the spikes.
These are the experimental spikes, these are the brown spikes.
One spike, another spike, another spike.
These are the experimental spikes.
But now if you model the spikes using
the extension of Hodgkin and Huxley and when I say
extension of Hodgkin and Huxley, I mean that the same formalism
exactly the same formalism
but adding additional currents
still carried by sodium, potassium, or calcium
but with different kinetics, so different Alphas
and different Betas for different channels, we know that there are
slow potassium channels, even slower then in
in the Hodgkin and Huxley case
there are ion channels in the membrane
that are sensitive to calcium, so the channels not only depend on
voltage but also on calcium, and so forth,
but it's the same formalism, and when you extend
the Hodgkin and Huxley formalism, you can get the firing patterns
essentially of every cell in the brain.
This is just one example, the green model
succeeds to replicate the firing of this particular cell
which is a cortical cell, nothing to do with
the squid giant axon, but still fires spikes
and spikes and spikes, but the pattern of activity
depends on these extra channels,
not only the generation of the single spike
but when will the next spike arrive, and the next spike arrive
depends on these other channels with the same
Hodgkin and Huxley formalism.
So it's a wonderful model because it not only captures
the spike in the squid giant axon, it captured the whole universal
phenomenon of a spike in any cell
and that's why we, in many ways
really adore Hodgkin and Huxley, because they gave us the tool
to simulate one of the two most important signals in the brain,
electrical signals : the spike.
The next thing we shall do, we'll go to the synaptic potential.