The role of hippocampus plays a key role in
several brain functions. Here I select
three of the most prominent ones. Memory,
perception of space and time. Between the
late 19th century and early 20th century,
scientists started to localize memory in
the brain. The easiest way to do that was to
correlate memory deficits with
physiological pathologies. In
particular, growing evidence showed a
correlation between memory and temporal
lobe, where the hippocampus is located.
The first tuning point happened with the
work of Scoville and Milner, published in
1957, and the famous patient Ernie
Mollison, who for decades was known as the
patient H.M. to protect his privacy. H.M.
was severely epileptic and his seizures
were resistant to anti-epileptic drugs.
In an attempt to alleviate the seizures,
the patient underwent a bilateral medial
temporal lobe resection. The operation
did reduce the seizure, but left the
patient with a profound amnesia. He could
not remember episodes after the
operation, anterograde amnesia, and
just before the surgery, retrograde
amnesia. During the 60s, the case of HM
promoted the quest for animal model of
amnesia, but the first attempts were not
completely successful. Around 1970,
several important developments took
place that improved the situation. First
of all, researchers developed
behavioral tests that were more
selective for the hippocampus. In
parallel, it became clear that there were
several forms of memory and only a subset
of them depends on the hippocampus. In
fact, we can distinguish a declarative
memory, which is a conscious
recollection of concepts and epithets
can be described in words, and a
procedural memory, which includes motor
skills and doesn't require a conscious
control and attention. Declarative
memory can be further divided in episodic
memory, which stores specific personal
experiences, and semantic memory, which
stores factual information. We now know
that the hippocampus is involved mostly
in episodic memory. Episodic memory is
the memory of episodes which occur in time
and space. So, does the hippocampus
specifically encode space and time? In
1971, O'Keefe and Dostrosky published a
short communication documenting the
first clear evidence on how hippocampal
cells represent space. In this classical
experiment, rats had microelectrodes
implanted in their brains, which
recorded the activity of several
hippocampal neurons while the animal
could move freely in an environment.
O'Keefe and Dostrosky observed that
eight electrodes over 76 correlated with
the position and direction of the animal.
They first described what we now call
place cells. This discovery simulated
O'Keefe and Nadel to formulate the first
of many special theories of the
hippocampus, which was described in the
influential book, Hippocampus as a
Cognitive Map, in 1978. In the following
years, researchers discovered other
cells that encode the relationship
between the animal and its location in
space. For example, in the 80s, Rank
discovered A-direction cells, which
encode where the animal is facing. At the
beginning of the new century, Edward and
May Britt Moser's group discovered grid
cells, which represent space in an
hexagonal coordinate system. Few years
later, Neil Burge's group discovered
boundary cells, which are sensitive to
boundaries. This line of research has
been so important for modern
neuroscience that in 2014, John O'Keefe
and May Britain Edward Moser received a
Nobel Prize in Physiology and Medicine.
Convincing evidence that the
hippocampus encodes time is most recent,
also due to difficulty in designing
unambiguous experiments. The
perception of time is a perception of an
order of sequence in time. So, if the
animal experiences a sequence of
stimuli, it perceives that a stimulus
occurred before, after, or at the same
time as another. To test if the animal
perceives the order of a sequence, the
animal is tested for the memory of this
order. Early evidence show how damage to
the hippocampus impairs memory of the
temporal order of events in both human and
animals. Other early studies associated
the activation of the human hippocampus
with encoding a recall of a sequence of
events. At the cellular level, initial
studies showing an association between
cell filings and time could not exclude a
special component. The work of Mann et al.
in 2007 described some of the first
convincing evidence for such an
association. In the experiment and the
encoding phase, rats alternated between
two sides of a testing enclosure as they
sampled a unique sequence of five odors.
At a subsequent test phase, rats were
presented with a randomly selected pairs
of non-adjacent sample odors and were
rewarded for choosing the odor that they
had appeared early in that sample phase.
The rat performed almost 80% correct,
showing they could track the order of
stimuli. The alternation of the location
of the odors allowed experimenters to
distinguish special clues from temporal
clues. In 2011, McDonald et al.
characterized cells in CN1 and named them
time cells, stressing an analogy with the
place cells. In fact, as play cells define
sequences in a spatial dimension, time
cells define sequences in a temporal
dimension. As you see, memory, space and
time are probably three phases of the same
phenomenon. In other words, the
hippocampus can bind stimuli to their
spatial temporal context, a form and a
methodic memory trace. The hippocampus
has an important regions also when we talk
about some types of pathologies. For
example, in the Alzheimer's disease, the
hippocampus has received substantial
attentions since initial alteration of
the pathology seems to start here before
spreading eventually to the rest of the
brain. Another important example is
epilepsy. As in the case of patient HM, the
temporal lobe is often the focus of
seizures, since the hippocampus
formation needs considerably less
current to elicit epileptiform activity
compared to other cortical areas.
Finally, the hippocampus, in particular
CA1, is highly vulnerable to ischemic and
hypoxic insults, making this region
critical also in cerebrovascular
diseases.