The hippocampus facilitated many
discoveries, due to its particular
structure and properties. First of all,
it has a relatively simple and ordered
structures, with four layers, where
excitatory cells populate only one
layer. The different hippocampal fields
are connected almost unidirectionally,
and fibers travel orthogonally to the
main dendritic axis of the pyramidal
cells. Furthermore, the synapses are
highly plastic, so that they can change
their strength in response to the pre- and
post-synaptic cells' behavior.
Finally, neurons can be grown in culture,
and acute occulturate slices survive in
vitro for a long time. Here, I would like to
present you a selection of key
discoveries made in the hippocampus,
which can be generalized to other brain
regions. In 1959, George Gray described
two types of synapses in cortex with
electron microscopy. Type I synapses
were more heavily stained, and the
synaptic specializations were
asymmetrical, in that the presynaptic
density was less intensely stained than
the postsynaptic density. Type I
synapses were usually associated with
androidic spines. Type II synapses had
pre- and post-synaptic density with the
same moderate staining intensity, and
they were found mainly in association
with dendritic shaft and neural somata.
The two types of synapses also exist in the
hippocampus, and the hippocampus was
used to identify the nature of those
synapse types. Using a combination of
intracellular and intracellular
recordings and staining technique, it
became clear that gray type 2 synapses are
inhibitory synapses mediated by GABA-A
receptors. Similarly, it was found that
type 1 synapses are excitatory synapses
mediated by AMPA receptors.
Furthermore, all the main hippocampus
pathways, the 3-synaptic loop I
mentioned in the previous lecture, were
found to be of type 1. The term synaptic
plasticity was introduced by Konofsky to
describe the changes in synaptic
efficacy that is assumed to be the basis of
information storage in the brain. In
1949, Hebb proposed a hypothesis on how
this synaptic change can take place.
According to Ebb's famous postulate,
when an axon of cell A is near enough to
excite a cell B and repeatedly and
persistently takes part in fighting it,
some growth process and metabolic change
takes place in one or both cells, such that
A's efficacy as one of the cells fighting B
is increased. Neuroscientists then
began to look for experimental evidence
to support Ebb's hypothesis.
Post-tetanic potentiation, or PTP, was a
candidate for a number of years. PTP
appeared as an enhanced synaptic
responses following a period of high
frequency stimulation of afferent
fibers. The main weakness of PTP is an
adequate mechanism for behavioral
learning, but it's limited duration. In
1996, LOMO reported that higher
stimulation frequencies and repeated
tetany can trigger longer lasting
enhancement. This observation allowed
Brice Lomo in 1970 to describe long-term
potentiation, or LTP, which can last for
hours and more. If activity-dependent
plasticity operated only to a
non-synaptic weights, saturation of
synaptic efficacy would eventually
occur, and a network with maximal
synaptic weights is incapable of
learning. Although potentiated
synapses may eventually decay to
baseline with time, an activity-driven
mechanism to allow the potentiation of
LFTP would enhance the computational
capability of the network. In addition,
long-term depression, or LTD, from
baseline values of synaptic efficacy
would further enhance the flexibility of
the system and increase its storage
capacity. Finally, having mechanism for
both potentiation and depression of
synaptic efficacy can tune the balance of
excitation and inhibition, which in turn
determines the overall stability of the
network. Danwiddi and Lynch report in
1978 the first evidence that LTD could be
achieved with low frequency
stimulation. However, several years
later, Judek and Beer found that
prolonged strain of low frequency
stimulation can produce a reliable LTD.
Judek and Beer went on to develop the
notion of graded bidirectional synaptic
modifiability. In this model, with
appropriate high or low frequency
simulation, a synapse could be
potentiated or depotentiated, thus
allow its efficacy to be set anywhere
within a range of approximately 50% of its
base value. Adult neurogenesis, the
maturation of new neurons in the adult
brain, can be considered a form of
structural plasticity. In the 60s,
Altman et al. first reported annulled
neurogenesis in dentate gyrus and
olfactory bulb, the only two regions
where adult neurogenesis is widely
recognized. In the dentate gyrus, new
cells originate from progenitor cells
located in the subgranular zone, a region
between the granule cell layers and the
ilus. Cells in this region divide,
presumably asymmetrically, to produce
some daughter cells that retain the
ability to divide and other cells that
became either neurons or glia. The new
cells migrate a short distance to the
granule cell layers and differentiate
into neurons. The extent of the process is
quite impressive. And for example, in a
young adult rat, several thousands of new
neurons are formed every day. Anyway,
substantial death of granule cells
results in a near static total population
of neurons. The role of neurogenesis in
the adult brain is still not completely
understood. It's the subject of an
intense experimental and theoretical
work. Few years after Berger described
the human EEG in 1924, Jung and Kohlmuller
found a prominent oscillatory activity
in the rabbit hippocampus, a frequency
between four and seven hertz, called
theta range. From these observations,
researchers started to correlate theta
activity with behavior. In the image
here, you can appreciate the extent of
this research. Today, we know that not
only TID activity is important for the
hippocampus function, but other types of
oscillation has been described and
associated with behavior. The
hippocampus has served as a test bench for
the development of a variety of new
methodology, such as novel recording
techniques. For example, in the
hippocampus, we have the first use of
microelectrodes for extracellular
recording of a single neuron discharge.
The extracellular recordings were used
fruitfully in the hippocampus to
characterize the two types of synapses as
we saw previously. Also intracellular
recordings were successful in the
hippocampus, and the first
comprehensive intracellular study used
the hippocampal pyramidal cells.
Finally, I would like to mention the
development of recording techniques
with two or four electrodes, called
respectively stereotrophs and
tetrophs. Those allow the study of neuron
ensemble and therefore phenomena that
occur more at the level of networks than
single cell.