DR. DAVID COX: So we've talked about motor memory.
And we've talked about emotional memory.
But the kind of memory we're probably most familiar with
is declarative memory--
the recall of stored facts and experiences.
These kinds of memory are thought to be subserved
by another subcortical structure, the hippocampus.
Like the amygdalae, the hippocampi come in a pair.
Your two hippocampi sit on either side of the thalamus just
below the amygdalae.
In Greek, hippocampus means seahorse.
And the hippocampus does look a bit like a seahorse.
Its tail curled at the very base of the brain.
The hippocampus is reciprocally connected
to both the cortex and subcortical structures.
Activity in the hippocampus is necessary for converting short-term memories
into long-term memories.
Consolidating an experience or fact held in short-term memory
into long-term storable code.
The hippocampus is also directly connected to the visual cortex,
and it plays a significant role in spatial navigation and memory.
Individuals with extensive damage to the hippocampus
have been occasionally reported throughout history.
One particularly famous case is that of Henry Molaison, a man who was
known as H.M. until his death in 2008.
In the 1950s, as a young man with intractable epilepsy, H.M.
had his hippocampi bilaterally removed, along with a large swath
of the adjacent brain.
At the time, doctors didn't know the critical function of the hippocampus
and consolidating memory.
They had recently found that removing parts of the brain
could relieve epilepsy.
Taking out a H.M.'s hippocampi did in fact decrease his epileptic seizures.
But it also left him with devastating memory impairments.
Specifically, H.M. could not form any new memories for facts or events--
a phenomenon known as anterograde amnesia.
He could only remember events from before his surgery.
Understandably, H.M. became the subject of many, many experiments
to study his condition.
Every day experimenters would come to him
and run experiments to try and understand his memory function.
Each day however, he would have to be introduced to his caretakers
again and again and again because he couldn't remember the new people.
Meanwhile, H.M.'s basal ganglia were left completely intact.
Accordingly, he had no difficulty learning new procedural tasks.
Every time researchers gave him a new task, for instance a tracing task,
they would have to re-explain it.
He insisted that he had never performed the task before, yet each time he did
the task, he'd get a little bit better.
As such, H.M. was able to form the procedural subconscious memory required
to learn a new task, but not the declarative conscious memory
needed to remember the experience of having performed the task.
What happened to H.M. was terrible.
But as some small silver lining, our understanding of the hippocampus
has been completely transformed by the research his condition enabled.
In addition to declarative memory, the hippocampus
also appears to play an important role in spatial navigation.
In 2014, the Nobel Prize in physiology and medicine
was awarded to three researchers who discovered
that cells in the hippocampus, and also in neighboring entorhinal cortex,
constitute a sort of positioning system in the brain.
These cells appear to create a dynamic map of the environment that
shifts as we move from place to place, and encodes
our specific location at all times.
The spatial navigation system is an area of ongoing research.
We still don't understand much about how it functions.
However, studies in rats have shown that between the entorhinal cortex
and the hippocampus, the brain forms a sort of topographic map.
Neurons, in the region of the map corresponding
to a particular place in the environment, fire as rats
move through that particular place.
This spatial navigation role and memory role in the hippocampus
may not be so different or dissociated from one another.
For instance, particularly if you're a rat,
most declarative memories-- things you need to remember--
are associated with particular places.
So there's a sense in which the hippocampus, perhaps, represents
context more than anything else.
How the hippocampus uses this context to consolidate memories though,
is still largely unknown.
However, it seems to involve LTP, or long term potentiation,
which we encountered in earlier modules of this course.
Specifically, LTP may allow the hippocampus to preferentially
strengthen certain patterns of neuronal firing,
and these patterns may encode those memories.
Interestingly, the hippocampus' plasticity, or its ability
to change its strength of his neuronal connections,
may also extend beyond LTP.
The hippocampus is one of only two regions
where neurogenesis, the birth and migration of new neurons,
has been found to occur in the adult brain.
We don't know much about how neurogenesis affects memory.
One hypothesis is that increased neurogenesis
makes it easier for the brain to write over previous memories.
This is supported by the fact that infants,
who show very high neurogenesis, are prodigious forgetters.
They don't form declarative memories for the first two years at least.